Guide to the Forman Family Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
- Papers of Charles W. Forman (1916-), 1947-2011; Series VII
  - Published writings
    - The Island Churches of the South Pacific (Orbis Books) - annotated galley proofs, ca. 1982 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Jesus Christ Frees and Unites, Education, 4/3-4, 1975, pp. 1, 4, 8. (Box 5a, Folder 89)
    - The Legacy of Charles W Forman, International Bulletin of Missionary Research, October, 2014, pp. 202-206 (Box 13, Folder 6a)
    - The Legacy of George Brown, International Bulletin of Missionary Research, Jan 1998, pp. 28-33. (Box 5a, Folder 89)
    - Madagascar, A Study in the Self-Propagating Church, Chapter V of Frontiers of the Christian World Mission, pp. 115-169., n.d. (Box 5a, Folder 89)
    - Mission, Church, and Sect in Oceania, ASAO Monograph no. 6, 1978, pp. 36-63. (Box 5a, Folder 89)
    - Mission Fission: Solidarity versus Salvation, Reflection, May 1976, pp. 4-8. (Box 5a, Folder 89)
    - Missionary Movements. (Dictionary article) (Box 5a, Folder 89)
    - Missionaries and Colonialism: The Case of the New Hebrides in the Twentieth Century, Journal of Church and State, Winter 1972, pp. 75-92. (Box 5a, Folder 89)
    - The Missionary Force of the Pacific Island Churches, International Review of Missions, 59, 1970, pp. 215-226. (Box 5a, Folder 89)
    - Missions in Papua New Guinea, Missionary Ideologies in the Imperialist Era, 1800-1920, 1982, pp. 23-37. (Box 5a, Folder 89)
    - The Missionary and the Third World, Yale Alumni Magazine, 36/6, 1973, pp. 18-23. (Box 5a, Folder 89)
    - Missions and Governments: Reflections on the Record, Missiology: An International Review, 9/4, 1981, pp. 409-422. (Box 5a, Folder 89)
    - Missions: Communist and Christian (Ms), 1951, 5 pp. (Published in the Presbyterian Tribune, Dec 1951. (Box 5a, Folder 89)
    - The New Communism, An appraisal, Yale Divinity News, Mar 1957, pp. 3-6. (Box 5a, Folder 89e)
    - Nordamerikanische Missionen, Evangelisches Kirchenlexikon, pp.770-775., n.d. (Box 5a, Folder 89e)
    - Norvin Hein: In Appreciation - Reflection., n.d. (Box 5a, Folder 89e)
    - Not by Bread Alone...The Intercollegian, 70/5, Jan 1953. (Box 5a, Folder 89e)
    - 150 Years of Discovery, Monday Morning, Jan 1987 (Box 5a, Folder 89e)
    - Die Okumenische Szene im Pazifik, Okumenische Rundschau, Oct 1990, pp. 454-462 (Box 5a, Folder 89e)
    - Openness--The New Missionary Calling of the Church (Manuscript), 18 pp., also in Princeton Seminary Bulletin, LIX/3, Jun 1966, pp. 12-22. (Box 5a, Folder 89e)
    - Pacific; Pacific Conference of Churches, Dictionary of the Ecumenical Movement, 1991, pp.769-771. (Box 5a, Folder 89e)
    - Pazifische Lander, Evangelisches Kirchenlexicon, 1991, pp. 341-344. (Box 5a, Folder 89e)
    - The Place of Foreign Missions in the Mission of the Church, The Student World, No. 4, 1957, pp. 370-377. (Box 5a, Folder 89e)
    - Preaching and Practice in Christianity and in Communism, The Christian Scholar, Dec 1958. (Box 5a, Folder 89e)
    - The Problem of Communism for Christian Missions, Union Seminary Quarterly Review, 7/1, Nov 1951, pp. 15-20. (Box 5a, Folder 89e)
    - Recent Developments in Pacific Island Christianity, Misisons Studies, Vol IX-1, 1992, pp. 24-39. (Box 5a, Folder 89)
    - Religious Pluralism and the Mission of the Church, International Bulletin, 6/1, 1982, pp. 5-8. (Box 5a, Folder 89)
    - Renewed in Faith, The Fourth World Meets PCC Assembly, 1971, pp. 182-190. (Box 5a, Folder 89)
    - Response to Norman Thomas, International Bulletin of Missionary Research, 1996, pp. 155-156 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - The South Pacific Style in the Christian Ministry, Missiology: An International Review, pp. 421-435., n.d. (Box 5a, Folder 89)
    - Theological Education in the South Pacific Islands: a quiet revolution, Journal de la Societe des Oceanistes, Dec 1969, pp. 151-167. (Box 5a, Folder 89g)
    - Theological Education TEF South Pacific, Education Newsletter, 1975, p. 4 (Box 5a, Folder 89g)
    - To Renew a Right Spirit: Fresh Challenges and Fresh Channels for Mission (4 lectures delivered at Columbia Theological Seminary, 1984 Nov 5-9, pp. 1-49) (Box 5a, Folder 89g)
    - Tonga's Tortured Venture in Church Unity, The Journal of Pacific History, Vo. 13, 1978, pp. 3-21. (Box 5a, Folder 89g)
    - Twelve Theses on Contemporary Missions, Occasional Bulletin, 4/1, Jan 1980. (Box 5a, Folder 89g)
    - The Wanted Missionary - Pacific Island Style, Frontier, 12/4, Nov 1969, pp. 267-273. (Box 5a, Folder 89g)
    - What the Church in America Can Learn from the Church in Europe, Cross, 4/2, Jan-Mar 1954, pp. 5-7. (Box 5a, Folder 89g)
    - Whom Have I in Heaven, Yale Divinity News, May 1965, pp. 13-14. (Box 5a, Folder 89g)
    - Whose Service is Perfect Freedom, Yale Divinity News, May 1960, pp. 3-4. (Box 5a, Folder 89g)
    - A World Lit by Lightning, Christian Century, 21 Dec 1955, pp. 1490-1492. (Box 5a, Folder 89g)
    - Miscellaneous book reviews (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Unpublished articles, papers, lectures
    - The 1930s Peace Movement, 2011 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - The Call to Perceptiveness (Manuscript), n.d. (Box 5b, Folder 90a)
    - The Call to Service (Manuscript), n.d. (Box 5b, Folder 90a)
    - The De-Westernizing of Christianity (Manuscript), 22 pp. with notes., n.d. (Box 5b, Folder 90a)
    - The Ecumenical Era in Missions (Manuscript), c. 1980. (Box 5b, Folder 90b)
    - Evangel in Today's World: Addresses given at the Annual meeting of the Department of Overseas Missions, Canadian Council of Churches, 1959 Feb (Box 5b, Folder 90b)
    - An Experiment in Inner-City Living, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Glimpses of the Missionary Work of Sallie Taylor Forman, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - An Historical Case Study: Polarization in Mission (Manuscript), 11 pp., annotated., n.d. (Box 5b, Folder 90b)
    - The impact of Western culture on Asia and Africa: Study Fellowship lecture, 1957 (Box 5b, Folder 90b)
    - "Intellectual Trajectories" - transcript of autobiographical talk given at Henry Koerner Center for Emeritus Faculty at Yale, 2006 Mar 27 (Box 5b, Folder 90b)
    - Marxist Image of Man (Manuscript), 14 pp., n.d. (Box 5b, Folder 90c)
    - A Memoir of the Partition, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Mission and the Church; Mission and the Religions; Mission and Liberation; Mission and Culture: Lectures delivered at Columbia Theological Seminary CTS/GAMB Missiology Study Event, 1984 Nov (Box 5b, Folder 90c)
    - The Missionary Message Today (Manuscript), 14 pp., ca. 1975 (Box 5b, Folder 90c)
    - The New Situation: The Mission Since 1945 (Manuscript), 1978. (Box 5b, Folder 90c)
    - "Other Gods", Summary of lectures on, 1955(?), 3 pp., ca. 1955 (Box 5b, Folder 90c)
    - Religion, Mr. Toynbee, and the Study of History (Manuscript), 1958. (Box 5b, Folder 90)
    - Religious Knowledge Among the Christians of Oceania (Manuscript) for ASAO meeting, Feb 1978, 18 pp. with bibliography. (Box 5b, Folder 90)
    - The Role of Mission Studies in Theological Education (Manuscript) ca. 1970, 24 pp. (Box 5b, Folder 90)
    - The Study of Pacific Island Christianity. Achievements, Resources, Needs (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Theological Education in the South Pacific Islands: Report of a Study Team, 1984 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Tomorrow's Missiology, (Manuscript), 15 pp. (Box 5b, Folder 90e)
    - Town and Gown, a report submitted to the India Council of the Presbyterian Board of Foreign Missions, 96 pp. (STM thesis), 1947 (Box 5b, Folder 90f-g)
    - The Travail of Religious Liberty (Manuscript), 1980, 21 pp. (Box 5b, Folder 90h)
    - What Has Become of Foreign Missions? (Manuscript), 1955, 6 pp. (Box 5b, Folder 90h)
    - Miscellaneous notes on missions from Asian and African churches (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Forman Committee Report re. improvements in Yale / New Haven relations, from Yale Bulletin, 1978 Feb (Box 8, Folder 124)
  - Organizational Activities
    - Foundation for Theological Education in Southeast Asia, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 91)
    - Theological Education Fund (TEF) / WCC: Membership lists, reports, 1960-1971 (Box 6, Folder 92)
    - TEF: Notes for speeches (Box 6, Folder 93)
    - TEF: Correspondence, incl. with Emilio Castro re. future of TEF and to WCC archivist re. errors in published histories of TEF, 1972-1998 (Box 6, Folder 94)
    - International Missionary Council, 1957-1973 (Box 6, Folder 95)
    - Commission on Ecumenical Mission and Relations (COEMAR), Presbyterian Church, U.S.A.: Documents re. purpose and stratery, 1968-1970 (Box 6, Folder 96)
    - COEMAR: Policy concerns, incl. re. Brazil, Mexico, 1969-1970 (Box 6, Folder 97)
    - COEMAR: Restraining order signed by CWF as COEMAR chair: The Interchurch Center et al vs. The National Black Economic Development Conference et al. Manifesto: "To the White Christian Churches and the Jewish Synagogues in the United States of America and All Other Racist Institutions" - Presentation by James Forman delivered and adopted by the National Black Economic Development Conference in Detroit, Michigan on April 26, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 98)
    - COEMAR: Re. Brazil, Ethiopia, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 99)
  - Material Related to Communism
    - Missionary Policy in the Christian Approach to Communism - statement and background papers, Foreign Missions Conference of North America, 1949-1950 (Box 6, Folder 100)
    - Presbyterian material incl: Letter from Presbyterian Board of Foreign Missions to Missionaries and Fraternal Workers (1950); Study Fellowship on the Christian Approach to Communism (Crisis Strategy Paper Number Two, 1951); Statement on Communism and the World Mission of the Church; Information Concerning the Experiences of Christians Under Communist Pressure, 1950-1951 (Box 6, Folder 101)
    - Reports, incl. of NCC Study Fellowship on the Christian Approach to Communism (1952);unidentified Committees 1 - 9 reports, 1952, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 102)
    - Koinonia Group letters; Study Fellowship on Christian Approach to Communism: Charles Forman, Hal Leiper, Catherine Alexander, Dick Shaull, etc.; associated documents, ca. 1951-1952 (Box 6, Folder 103)
    - Miscellaneous memos and reports, incl. NCC memo by Samuel McCrea Cavert, "Memorandum on the Protestant Clergy and the McCarthy - Matthew Episode", ca. 1950-1954 (Box 6, Folder 104)
    - Communism in East Germany, incl. "Kerk en Wereld" circular letters from H. Kohlbrugge, 1951-1961 (Box 7, Folder 105)
    - Christianity and Communism in China, 1950-1960 (Box 7, Folder 106-107)
    - Christianity and Communism in India, 1951-1954 (Box 7, Folder 108-109)
    - Christianity and Communism in other countries, 1950-1956 (Box 7, Folder 110)
    - Miscellaneous articles, clippings, brochures, leaflets re. Communism, 1941-1958 (Box 7, Folder 111-113)
  - Collected Material
    - Miscellaneous articles, clippings, brochures re. mission work (Box 7, Folder 114-115)
    - Asian Center for Theological Studies, Korea (Box 7, Folder 116)
    - Mission work in India and China (Box 7, Folder 117)
    - Mission work in Japan, Asian surveys (Box 8, Folder 118)
    - Mission work in Indonesia, Philippines (Box 8, Folder 119)
    - Mission work in Africa, Latin America, Caribbean (Box 8, Folder 120)
    - Miscellaneous circular letters from missionaries (Box 8, Folder 121)
    - Report of the Justice and Peace Consultation, Nouméa, New Caledonia, 1984 Oct (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Re. church and missions in Pacific area, 1957-1982, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Woodcut of great seal of the Taiping Heavenly Kingdom, purchased at Nanjing museum in 1986 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Biographical information
    - "My Pilgrimmage in Mission" article from International Bulletin of Missionary Research (Jan 1994); article from "Who's Who" 2002 (See also autobigraphical talk given in 2006, Box 5b), 1994, 2002 (Box 8, Folder 122)
    - Oral history interviews; Tribute to CWF on his retirement from Board of Foundation for Theological Education in South East Asia, by Gerald Anderson, 1992, 2001, 2002 (Box 8, Folder 123)
    - Tribute to CWF on retirement as Honorary Trustee of Foundation for Theological Education in South East Asia by Gerald Anderson, 2007 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Obituary, program from memorial service, tribute delivered by Gerald Anderson, 2014, 2015 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Audio-visual Material
    - Slides
      - Slides documenting Charles Forman's travels and work in Botswana, China, Cook Islands, East Africa, Egypt, Fiji, Indonesia, Madagascar, Mexico, Micronesia, New Guinea, Samoa, Solomon Islands, Vanuatu, West Africa, and elsewhere. The slides primarily depict churches, church leaders, seminaries, and seminary students and faculty., 1950s-1980s (Box 11)
    - Photographs
      - Theological Education Fund Committee of the World Council of Churches, meeting in Edinburgh, 1960 (Box 12, Folder 8)
      - Founding conference for Pacific Theological College, Suva, 1961 (Box 12, Folder 8)
      - Theological Education Fund Committee, meeting in London, 1965 (Box 12, Folder 8)
      - Theological Education Fund Committee, meeting in Aarhus, Denmark, 1966 (Box 12, Folder 8)
      - Consultation on Theological Education in the Pacific, Suva, 1985 (Box 12, Folder 9)
      - Kava ceremony at Pacific Conference of Churches Assembly, Samoa, 1986 (Box 12, Folder 9)
      - Forman Memorial Church, Lahore, 1989 (Box 12, Folder 9)
      - ATESEA meeting, Manila, 1989 (Box 12, Folder 9)
      - Church of North India Seminary Church, Saharanpur, 2001 (Box 12, Folder 9)
      - Miscellaneous photos of churches, church leaders, seminaries in China, Philippines, Indonesia, Pacific, 1981-1986 (Box 12, Folder 9)
- Addendum, 1849-1984; Series VIII
  - Charles W. Forman (1821-1894)
    - Genealogical information - Newton, Janvier families, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Re. Founding of Forman Christian College; Founders Days addresses, 1927-1959 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Family correspondence, 1877-1883 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence: CWF to/from others, 1852-1890 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Writings of CWF: "Indoor preaching to non Christians"; "Boys School"; "How shall we deal with Hindu and Muhammadan enquirers and converts who have more than one wife?", ca. 1849 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Obituary of CWF, excerpted from Annual Mission Report of 1895 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - John Newton Forman (1863-1917)
    - Bible annotated by JNF, 1907 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Mary P. Forman
    - Diary, 1927-1928 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Composition book containing handwritten sketches of events and people in India, with small photo of Mary P. Forman enclosed, ca. 1920s (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - March Family
    - Frederick William March
      - Autobiography by March; biographical narrative by son, Hal, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 7)
      - "Diaries and Letters" - chronological excerpts of diary entries and letters describing his journey to Syria and mission work with Syria Mission, 1873-1880 (Box 9, Folder 8)
      - Family correspondence, from Beirut and Suk al Gharb, 1930-1935 Sep (Box 9, Folder 9)
      - Family correspondence re. death of FWM and tributes, 1935 Oct (Box 9, Folder 10)
      - Writings of FWM: "The Bandit of Bishmizine" - as retold by Amy March Forman (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Jennie Hill March
      - Biographical info, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 12)
      - Excerpts from JHM's diary, including from Ijbea, Mount Lebanon, 1895-1899 (Box 9, Folder 13)
      - Letters to children, from Zahleh, Syria, 1918-1934 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - March children
      - Correspondence of Elizabeth to family, from Syria, 1935-1948 (Box 9, Folder 15)
      - Reminiscences of Arthur and son, Bob re. life in Syria, 1983, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Douglas and Amy March Forman family
    - Douglas N. Forman, Sr.
      - Correspondence to.from family, incl. from Allahabad, 1919-1939 (Box 9, Folder 17)
      - Correspondence from others, 1919-1958 (Box 9, Folder 18)
      - Correspondence re. Dr. Chen-Jen Han / Christian Medical Council for Overseas Work, 1954-1957 (Box 9, Folder 19-20)
      - Writings of DNF, incl. "The Serpent's Body"; "The Objectives of Medicine"; "Causes of Ill-Health on the Campus", 1920-1924 (Box 9, Folder 21)
      - News clippings; biographical information, 1920-1961 (Box 9, Folder 22)
    - Amy March Forman
      - Correspondence to children, primarily from Allahabad, 1935-1940 (Box 9, Folder 23-25)
      - Letter from Robert E. Speer re. death of her father, Frederick William March, 1935 (Box 10, Folder 26)
      - Transcript of record reminiscences, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 27)
      - Hiking stories (hiking in India) (Box 10, Folder 28)
      - Obituary, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 29)
    - Children of Douglas and Amy
      - Douglas, Jr.: "A family trip", n.d. (Box 10, Folder 30)
      - Kenneth and wife: obituaries, 1979 (Box 10, Folder 31)
      - Reminiscences re. parents by Catherine and Peggy, 1983-1984 (Box 10, Folder 32)
  - Documentation of Mission Work in India
    - Book: History of A.P. Missions in India (Box 10, Folder 33)
    - Bulletins, articles, minutes, 1953-1956 (Box 10, Folder 34)
    - Ewing Christian College - booklets, 1929-1958 (Box 10, Folder 35)